southernwater.co.uk 2014-05-29

# Privacy statement

By continuing to visit any of our websites,   
or providing us data, or contacting us, you agree to our use of your personal information in accordance with this privacy statement,   
or as we may otherwise tell you at the  
time of collection.

 **This privacy statement was last updated on May 24, 2012. Please read it carefully.**

  1. **Introduction**  
    * Southern Water Services Ltd (‘Southern Water’) recognises the importance of respecting your personal privacy and also the need to have in place appropriate safeguards surrounding the processing of personal data. 

We have notified our processing of personal data to, and are registered with, the Information Commissioner's Office - Reg. No. Z5449252.

Whether via our website, letter, email or another method, we assure you that we will only use personal information about you in accordance with this statement and our registered details held on the public register administered by the Information Commissioner and available via their website [www.ico.gov.uk](http://www.ico.gov.uk/)

This privacy statement explains how we may use information supplied by, or collected from you, or obtained via other sources. Where we refer to your ‘Personal Data’ we mean information that is held by us, that identifies and relates to you as an individual and where you are the subject and focus.

  2. **Links to third party websites and embedded content**  
    * Our websites contain links to, and may embed content from, other online services provided by other organisations. Southern Water is not responsible for the content or privacy practices of those websites and accepts no responsibility of liability for those sites. Where third-party content is included within our websites we will point this out, where it may not be obvious. 

Such services may include; YouTube videos, Google Maps, and online payment.

  3. **Protecting your information online**  
    * There is an element of risk involved with sending information via the Internet. We urge you to take appropriate precautions to protect your personal information when accessing on-line resources. Ensuring your operating system and Internet browser are updated with relevant security patches, and the use of other security products, can help reduce this risk.
  4. **How long will Southern Water keep my information?**  
    * We will only retain your information for as long as is necessary for the purpose(s) the information was collected.
  5. **How do I change my preferences for receiving marketing material?**  
    * Should you wish to amend your preference for receiving information about water related goods and services from us, or carefully selected third parties, please email your name and customer reference, together with your instruction to [dataprotection@southernwater.co.uk](mailto:dataprotection@southernwater.co.uk) (standard email) or write to: Data Protection Officer, Southern Water, Southern House, Yeoman Road, Worthing, BN13 3NX.
  6. **How do I find out what personal data Southern Water hold about me?**  
    * If you wish to ensure the details we hold about you are correct and up to date, this can be done via our [website](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/your-account/change-your-details.asp). Most queries and updates can be handled online – such as requesting [copy bills](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/about-your-bill/request-a-copy-of-your-bill/default.asp), or if you are [moving house](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/moving-house/default.asp). 

A list of Customer Service contact details is also available [here](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/about-us/contact-us/default.asp).

If you require a full Subject Access Request, then this must be done in writing. 

With limited exceptions, the Data Protection Act 1998, provides you the right to make a formal request for the Personal Data held by a Data Controller – called a Subject Access Request, or ‘SAR’.  However, the right of access only covers recorded ‘Personal Data’.  

As such, any information requested must be specifically about you, where you are the subject and focus, rather than relate to some event or other matter. 

If you wish to make a SAR you will need to pay a fee and provide proof of identity, or authorisation if acting for someone else, and also provide sufficient information to assist us locate the Personal Data of interest. Confirmation of what is required, and assistance with the process, can be obtained via: [dataprotection@southernwater.co.uk](mailto:dataprotection@southernwater.co.uk) (standard email) or write to: Data Protection Officer, Southern Water, Southern House, Yeoman Road, Worthing, BN13 3NX.

  7. **Who do I contact if I have a query about Southern Water's privacy practices?**  
    * If you wish to ensure the details we hold about you are correct and up to date, this can be done via our [website](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/your-account/change-your-details.asp). Most queries and updates can be handled online – such as requesting [copy bills](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/about-your-bill/request-a-copy-of-your-bill/default.asp), or if you are [moving house](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/moving-house/default.asp). 

A list of Customer Service contact details is also available [here](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/about-us/contact-us/default.asp).

If you have any queries about your privacy when using our online services, or concerning our use of personal data, please contact our Data Protection Officer at [dataprotection@southernwater.co.uk](mailto:dataprotection@southernwater.co.uk) (standard email) or by post: Data Protection Officer, Southern Water, Southern House, Yeoman Road, Worthing, BN13 3NX.

The Information Commissioner’s Office (ICO) is the UK’s independent authority set up to uphold information rights. The ICO has extensive guidance on its [website](http://www.ico.gov.uk/) and can provide advice via; post, fax, email and telephone helpline.

  8. **How will I know if this privacy statement is updated?**  
    * We will update this privacy statement in response to company, visitor and customer feedback and/or to comply with changes to relevant legislation. In the event of material changes to this statement, or how personal information is used, we will post an appropriate announcement on the Southern Water website home page. 

The date of the last amendment is displayed on the right hand side of this page.

  9. **How do I update my information?**  
    * It is important that your information is kept up to date. [Our website](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/at-home/your-bill-and-account/your-account/change-your-details.asp) enables customers to keep us informed of required changes so that our records can be amended.
  10. **Email messages**  
    * If you contact us by email, or provide your email address for us to contact you, we may use the details provided to contact you about anything to do with your query, or managing your account. If you no longer wish us to contact you by email, please let us know and, if necessary, provide alternative contact details. 

**Standard email  
**Some contact facilities use standard email to provide the details entered. If you choose to use standard email to transmit information to us you are advised not to include any sensitive details.

  11. **What information is collected from visitors to our websites?**  
    * Southern Water does not use cookie-based tools to track visitor activity. We do analyse some information about visits to our websites to help us understand user preferences so that we can make regular improvements to site content and navigation. The sort of information captured includes; how many people visit our site and which pages are the most popular. This activity **does not** use cookies and **does not** record personally identifiable information.
  12. **What are cookies?**  
    * Cookies are small text files that can be added to your computer by websites with the aim of making the site work, improve a user's experience and/or make their activity more efficient. 

Often cookies are used to provide useful information to the owners of the site – such as how many people visit or the most popular pages and, occasionally, to track activity across the Internet.

New legislation came into force in the UK on 26th May 2011 that affects most web sites. If cookies are used on a site, the Privacy and Electronic Communications (EC Directive) (Amendment) Regulations 2011 requires that certain information must be given to visitors and they must give their consent to the placing of any non-essential cookies.

Most web browsers allow some control of cookies through browser settings. 

More information about cookies, including how to block and/or delete them, via a range of common browsers, can be found at these third-party websites: [www.aboutcookies.org](http://www.aboutcookies.org/default.aspx?page=1) or [www.allaboutcookies.org](http://www.allaboutcookies.org/).

  13. **Does Southern Water use cookies?**  
    * Our use of cookies varies depending upon which of our websites, and which functions you access. 

We've taken steps to remove and limit the need for cookies on its websites to comply with legislation that came into effect in May 2011.

One cookie is essential for our websites to operate and is created on arrival, however this file is automatically removed when you end your browser session. 

You may configure your computer to refuse cookies from this, or any other website, but certain areas of our site require the use of cookies to operate and will not function properly without them.

**Cookie use  
**  

To comply with legislation, which came into effect on May 26, 2011, visitors to our websites are asked for their permission to use non-essential cookies when accessing content that requires their use.

Your browser may copy other files, such as images, from this and other sites and store them on your computer so that pages load quicker after your first visit.

Please note that other websites linked on this site might make use of their own cookies. We encourage visitors to ascertain the privacy practices of the website they access.

  14. **Should I accept cookies from Southern Water?**  
    * We only use cookies to enhance your use of our websites. **We do not use cookies to monitor or analyse your browsing activity**.

Where non-essential cookies are required, you will be informed and given the choice as to whether to accept them, but certain features or our site may not function without acceptance.

Once cookies are accepted from Southern Water, a file is added to your computer and you will not need to give permission again if you revisit our site within 12 months – unless:

• You change computer  
• You delete the acceptance cookie manually  
• It's removed along with other cookies by your Internet security software.

Please note that other websites linked on this site might make use of their own cookies. We encourage visitors to ascertain the privacy practices of the website they access.

  15. **YouTube cookies**  
    * We embed videos from YouTube using YouTube’s privacy-enhanced mode. 

This mode may set cookies on your computer once you click on the YouTube video player, but YouTube will not store personally-identifiable cookie information for playbacks of embedded videos using the privacy-enhanced mode.

For more information visit YouTube's [embedding videos information page](https://support.google.com/youtube/answer/171780?hl=en).

  16. **Careers online recruitment section**  
    * We will only use the information you provide in connection with your job application and will not disclose your information or use it for any other purpose. 

All the information we collect is stored securely on a centralised recruitment database. 

The processing and administration of any job application may be undertaken in a country outside the European Economic Area. 

The information will be stored securely for up to 12 months after your last visit.

  17. **Online payments**  
    * We use third party specialists to process payments made via our websites. 

These include Santander Bill Pay and WorldPay. 

Using these online services will necessitate transfer or interaction through their website via content provided by them.

  18. **Does Southern Water share personal data with anyone else?**  
    * The information you provide us, or that we hold about you, may be used by our staff and other agents, such as or specialist-contracted data processors, to help manage our service to you.

Unless you have notified us of an objection, we may also provide you information on water-related goods or services that we believe may be of benefit.

To help prevent and detect fraud or debt we may need to exchange details with credit reference and fraud prevention agencies.

For billing purposes, we may exchange information with the company that supplies your drinking water or is responsible for removing your waste water, where this is not Southern Water, in order that our and their records are as up to date as possible.

We may also provide information when under a duty to do so, perhaps by a Court order or statutory obligation, or in response to legitimate requests for the purpose of the prevention or detection of crime or  the apprehension and prosecution of offenders.

  19. **Does Southern Water record telephone calls?**  
    * If you contact us by telephone, your call may be recorded for training and service-related purposes. Some out-bound calls, from us to you, may also be recorded.
  20. **Does Southern Water monitor email communications?**  
    * To protect our staff and systems we may monitor email communications and may restrict delivery under certain circumstances.
  21. **Making automated decisions**  
    * Some processing may be automated. Such processing may occur in limited circumstances when setting up or managing your account with us.
  22. **Surveys and competitions**  
    * We occasionally collect information for surveys, or competitions. Participation in such activities is voluntary and individuals therefore have a choice whether or not to provide their information. How your data may be used will be in accordance with this Statement or as explained at the time of collection.
  23. **Where might my information be transferred?**  
    * We may use your information, or provide it to contracted suppliers who work on our behalf, both within the UK and abroad.

We will only transfer personal information outside the European Economic Area where our notification to the Information Commissioner and/or the provisions of the Data Protection Act 1998, specifically allows it. If such transfer occurs, we will put in place appropriate measures to safeguard the data.

  24. **Enhanced security of data transmission**  
    * We recognise the concerns that some people have about sending personal information using the Internet and operate enhanced security measures.

When you visit certain areas of our web site you may be notified, by a ‘security alert notification’, that you are about to view pages over a secure connection. 

Any information you exchange within these areas cannot be viewed by anyone else on the Internet.

The transfer of personal information is completed using secure servers. These servers use high level 128 bit SSL (Secure Socket Layer) encryption - which is a leading security standard in the e-commerce industry. 

For your peace of mind, your Web browser may display a padlock, or other, symbol to indicate the site is secure. Clicking the symbol will confirm the security provided.

  25. **Debt recovery**  
    * The Water Industry Act 1991 provides water companies the power to charge for services provided and to demand and recover monies owed.

Charges for water and wastewater services arise out of the occupancy of a property connected, pursuant to s142-s144 of the Water Industry Act 1991 and, therefore, charges are statutory and not contractual.

If you owe us money and do not repay in accordance with our payment terms we will notify you of our intention to file a default and if still unpaid we will inform a credit reference agency.

We may make periodic searches of our own records, via credit reference agency, or other sources, to manage your account with us, including whether to review your existing payment terms or recover monies due to us.

If you have used our services, vacate the premises and do not make payments that you owe us, we will trace your whereabouts and recover debts.

  26. **Credit reference agencies**  
    * We may share your personal information with Credit Reference (CRA) and Fraud Prevention Agencies (FPA) in order to verify your identity for the purposes of fraud prevention and to assist us in managing your account and providing services to you appropriately – for example, if you do not pay your bill and we need to trace or otherwise contact you.

• [Supply and use of data](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/about-us/about-southern-water/our-customer-promise/privacy/craGuide/default.asp)  
• [What we do](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/about-us/about-southern-water/our-customer-promise/privacy/craGuide/what-we-do.asp)  
• [What they do](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/about-us/about-southern-water/our-customer-promise/privacy/craGuide/what-they-do.asp)  
• [How to find out more](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/about-us/about-southern-water/our-customer-promise/privacy/craGuide/more-information.asp)  
• View, download or print our [CRA Guide](http://www.southernwater.co.uk/pdf/about-us/Our-customer-promise/CRA_guide.pdf)
